Dorothy Wrinch Papers, 1901-1983 (bulk 1919-1975)
Sophia Smith Collection
Dorothy Wrinch papers
1901-1983
1919-1975
Wrinch, Dorothy, 1894-1976
MS 178
35 boxes; oversize materials; 2 volumes (13 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Crystallographer, Biochemist, Mathematician, Physicist. Papers contain original manuscripts; models; printed material; publications and writings; notebooks and scrapbooks; as well as extensive correspondence which illuminate her research and views on crystal structure, cyclols, peptides, mineral twins, x-ray methods, insulin, and polyhedra.
Dorothy Maud Wrinch was a chemist, biologist, and physicist most famous for her development of the cyclol theory. Throughout her career, she used her background in mathematics to apply math to biology, and was an important early figure in molecular biology.
Wrinch was born in 1894 in Rosario, Argentina to English parents Ada Minnie Souter and Hugh Edward Hart Wrinch. In 1913 Wrinch received a scholarship to Girton College, a residential women's college at Cambridge. There she studied pure and applied mathematics, earning her BA degree with first-class honors in 1916. Wrinch stayed a fourth year at Girton to study mathematical logic with Bertrand Russell. After earning her MA in 1918, Wrinch taught mathematics at University College, London while completing her MSc (1920) and DSc (1922). She moved to Oxford in 1922 after marrying John Nicholson. (They would separate in 1930.) Wrinch taught mathematics to women at Oxford and earned her second MSc in 1924. Her daughter, Pamela, was born in 1928. The next year, Wrinch was the first woman awarded a DSc from Oxford. She diverged from her more prominent mathematical writings in 1930 when she published the sociological work Retreat from Parenthood under the pseudonym Jean Ayling.
In the 1930s, Wrinch expanded her studies to biology and chemistry, and traveled to several locations throughout Europe for fellowships. She came to the United States in 1935 on a Rockefeller Foundation Fellowship, and after the outbreak of World War II, was to live in the United States for the remainder of her life. Wrinch lectured at Johns Hopkins University from 1939 to 1941, after which she became a visiting research professor for Smith, Mount Holyoke, and Amherst Colleges. Wrinch remarried in 1941, to Amherst College biology professor Otto C. Glaser, and became a U.S. citizen in 1943. It was during this time that Wrinch developed and first published her controversial cyclol theory of protein structure. Wrinch wrote extensively on this theory, and defended it enthusiastically at all points. Though she had some supporters, notably Irving Langmuir, she had many more critics, among them Linus Pauling. Though her theory was eventually applied successfully, Wrinch's overzealous and singular focus on cyclol theory alienated her from many in the scientific community.
Wrinch was appointed a Smith College professor in 1942, and for the next three decades, researched, lectured, and taught graduate student seminars there. During summers, she and her family lived in Woods Hole, Massachusetts where she taught and lectured in physics. Her research during the 1940s focused on developing techniques for interpreting complex crystal structure x-rays, as well as mineralogy. In 1954 Wrinch finally won definitive support for her cyclol theory when cyclol bonds were found in ergot alkaloids. Throughout the course of her career, she published 192 works, a list of which can be found in Marjorie Senechal's Structures of Matter and Patterns in Science (in SERIES VIII. SMITH COLLEGE - Symposium).
Otto Glaser died in 1951 and Wrinch's daughter Pamela was killed in a fire in 1975. Wrinch moved to Woods Hole after her retirement from Smith in 1971. She died February 11, 1976.
The Dorothy Wrinch Papers contain original manuscripts; models; printed material; publications and writings; notebooks and scrapbooks; as well as extensive correspondence which illuminates her research and views on crystal structure, cyclols, peptides, mineral twins, x-ray methods, insulin, and polyhedra. Also included are articles by colleagues and contemporaries, lecture notes, grant correspondence, models and photographs. There are also selected letters and writings by her daughter Pamela Wrinch Schenkman (1927-75).
This collection is organized into eleven series:
I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS (1933-63, n.d.)
II. PHOTOGRAPHS (1964-87)
III. CORRESPONDENCE (1924-75, n.d.)
IV. GRANTS (1930-64)
V. PUBLICATIONS (1919-65)
VI. WRITINGS (1930-1970, n.d.)
VII. MODELS AND STRUCTURES (undated)
VIII. SMITH COLLEGE (1940-71, n.d.)
IX. MISCELLANEOUS (1923-69)
X. PAMELA WRINCH (1945-54, n.d.)
XI. NOTEBOOKS (1930-69, n.d.)
The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection without any additional restrictions.
Dorothy Wrinch donated her papers to the Sophia Smith Collection in 1976.
Biochemistry--Study and teaching--History--Sources; Crystallography--Study and teaching; Smith College--Faculty--History--Sources; Physicists--United States--Biography--Sources; Women biochemists--United States--Biography--Sources; Women physicists--United States--Biography--Sources; Women scientists--United States--Biography--Sources; Bohrs, Niels Henrik David, 1885-1962; Hodgekins, Dorothy Crowfoot; Neville, Eric Harold,1889-; Pauling, Linus, 1901- --Correspondence; Russell, Bertrand, 1872-1970; Harker, David--Correspondence; Langmuir, Irving, 1881-1957--Correspondence; Sobotka, Harry, 1899-1965--Correspondence; Stoll, Arthur, b. 1887 --Correspondence; Thompson, D'Arcy Wentworth, 1860-1948--Correspondence; Wrinch, Dorothy, 1894-1976; Wrinch family
Related materials in the Smith College Archives: Faculty files; President's Office files (correspondence re: appointment); and files on 1976 symposium in honor of Dorothy Wrinch.
Julian, Maureen M. "Wrinch, Dorothy Maud." Susan Ware, ed. Notable American Women: A Biographical Dictionary Completing the 20th Century. Cambridge, MA: The Belknap Press, 2004.
- I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS 1933-63, undated, .5 linear ft.
  This series includes biographical material, clippings, and obituaries about Dorothy Wrinch; plus her legal papers, college appointments, and list of publications. There are also personal notes, diaries, and address books. Also included is information about her father Hugh Edward Hart Wrinch, and Otto Glaser (1881-1951), her second husband. For biographical material on her daughter Pamela Wrinch Schenkman, see SERIES X.
- II. PHOTOGRAPHS 1964-87, .5 linear ft.
  This series includes photographs of Dorothy Wrinch, Otto Glaser, Pamela Wrinch, and miscellaneous friends.
- III. CORRESPONDENCE 1924-75, undated, 1.5 linear ft.
  This series is organized into three subseries: Family, Individuals, and Miscellaneous. The correspondence is arranged alphabetically. Family correspondence includes letters regarding Otto Glaser's death, 1951. Individuals' correspondence is in alphabetical order by last name of correspondent. It includes both professional and personal correspondence to and from Wrinch, and occasional third party correspondence. The subseries includes copies made from the Bertrand Russell Archives, McMaster University. Significant correspondents include crystallographer David Harker (1938-46); chemists Linus Pauling (1938-41), Irving Langmuir (1938-46), Harry Sobotka (1937-65), Arthur Stoll (1955-61), Dorothy Crowfoot Hodgkins (1936-69), and naturalist D'Arcy Thompson (1924-43). Correspondence with Eric Neville and Harry Sobotka includes Wrinch's notes with the letters. Miscellaneous correspondence includes correspondence between Langmuir, Huggins, Pauling, Lamb, and Harker, 1938-40; and financial and purchase orders; the Princeton project, 1946-47; reprint requests; wedding congratulations; and unidentified correspondence. Some correspondence can also be found in SERIES VI. WRITINGS, SERIES VIII. SMITH COLLEGE, and SERIES XI. NOTEBOOKS.
- IV. GRANTS 1930-64, .5 linear ft.
  This series includes correspondence and miscellaneous material from the Office of Naval Research (1947-1958), National Science Foundations (1961-1964), Rockefeller Foundation (1930, 1935-40), and miscellaneous grants.
- V. PUBLICATIONS 1919-65, 1.25 linear ft.
  This series includes reprints, articles, abstracts, and newspaper articles published by Dorothy Wrinch. There are also drafts of her work with comments and notes by Wrinch and others, and some diagrams and illustrations.
- VI. WRITINGS 1930-1970, undated, 3.25 linear ft.
  This series includes Wrinch's unpublished written work and is organized chronologically. It includes manuscripts, non-technical unpublished writings, essays concerning the direction of her work, speeches, diagrams, notes (both technical and non-technical), and marked reprints. There are notes, diagrams, and drafts relating to twinning and symmetry; early studies on peptides; notes on bacitracin and insulin, and correspondence and notes from and with P.B. Medawar, D'Arcy Thompson, and H.B. Vickery.
- VII. MODELS AND STRUCTURES undated, .5 linear ft.
  This series includes models and structures of Wrinch's work, in various forms. Most of the material is photographs, negatives, diagrams, orders for models, and descriptions of models. There are also three-dimensional models and two scrapbooks in Oversize Materials.
- VIII. SMITH COLLEGE 1940-71, undated, .5 linear ft.
  This series contains material from Wrinch's time at Smith College as a visiting professor, researcher, and lecturer in the physics department. Material includes class and seminar notes, schedules, examinations, and student recommendations.
- IX. MISCELLANEOUS 1923-69, .5 linear ft.
  This series contains miscellaneous material, including bibliographic references, lists of people, memorials to Bohr and Sobotka, Physical Society material, reprints and writings by others, and clippings.
- X. PAMELA WRINCH 1945-54, undated, .5 linear ft.
  This series includes biographical material and clippings about Wrinch's daughter, Pamela Wrinch Schenkman, as well as her daughter's writings on international relations and some personal writings.
- XI. NOTEBOOKS 1930-69, undated, 1.75 linear ft.
  This series contains Wrinch's scientific notes, clippings, reprints, and correspondence and is arranged chronologically. The numbering system on the notebooks (1-36) was done by the compiler, not Wrinch, and was used only for points of reference. The dates on some of the notebooks were determined by examining some of the dated information inside, which was sketchy at best. Some folders have subject notations on the front. These are not meant to be definitive, but rather an indication of some material within.
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS
  - Contents (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Biographical information 1956-77, [see also OVERSIZE MATERIALS - Diplomas] (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Newspaper clippings, including obituaries 1941-76 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - "Dorothy Wrinch and the Rockefeller Foundation Grants" by Sibilla E. Kennedy 1983 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Legal documents 1922-62 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Three College appointment, announcement, and publicity 1941 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Lists of publications during 1932-65 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Hugh Edward Hart Wrinch (father): "Details of Career," 1901 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Otto Glaser: Obituary and memorials 1951 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Personal notes 1933-35, 1954-56, 1961-64, undated (Box 1, Folder 10-12)
  - Diaries 1937-39, 1947-48, 1953-63 (Box 2, Folder 1-6)
  - Address books (Box 2, Folder 7-8)
- SERIES II. PHOTOGRAPHS 1936-66, undated
  - Dorothy Wrinch 1936-66, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Wedding photos 1941 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Otto Glaserundated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Pamela Wrinchundated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneousundated (Box 3, Folder 5)
- SERIES III. CORRESPONDENCE 1924-75, undated
  - Family
    - Pamela Wrinch 1931, 1938, 1951, 1961-66, [see also SERIES X. PAMELA WRINCH] (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Letters re: Otto's death 1951 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Otto Glaser to D.W. and others 1941-43, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Muriel Wrinch-Schulzundated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Individuals
    - A 1936-70 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - American Chemical Society 1946-47, 1962-64 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Anslow, Gladys 1941-43, 1963-69 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Anslow with others 1946, 1951-57, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Astbury, William T. 1936-7, 1951, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - B 1940-1965 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Beevers, Arnold 1970 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Bergmann, Max 1937 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Bernal, J. Desmond (includes notes on a discussion) 1936-39, [see also Irving Langmuir correspondence] (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Bohr, Niels 1938-39, 1946, 1957, [see also SERIES IX. MISCELLANEOUS - Memorials: Niels Bohr] (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Booth, Andrew Donald (includes calculation notes) 1946-48, 1951, undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Bragg, Lawrence 1943, undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Brenner, Max 1960-61, undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Buerger, Martin 1943-45 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - C 1936-1970 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Clowes, G. H. A. 1938, 1955-56 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Crew, Francis (includes notes on their relationship) 1934 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - D 1937-70 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Deutsch, Adam 1936-37 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Diller, Irene Corey 1957, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Donnay, Jose and Gabrielle 1946, 1951, 1956-57, 1970, [see also SERIES VI. WRITINGS - Research Notes - Twinning: notes for companion paper with Donnay] (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - E 1944-70 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Emery, Alden H. 1941-42 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Evans, Howard T. 1947 (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Evans, R. C. 1953 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - F 1936-70 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Fajans, Kasimir 1942-43 (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - Fankuchen, I. 1950-55, 1961-62, [see also Jerome Karle correspondence] (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Fodor, A. (includes notes) 1937 (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - Franklin, Rosalind (includes notes on a talk) 1955-56 (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - Fry, Margery (includes obituary and painting) 1940-41, 1943, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - G 1941-70 (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Glenn, Alan 1961-63, 1966-70 (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - H 1932-68 (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - Harker, David 1938, 1952-54, 1967, [see also Misc. correspondence and Langmuir correspondence] (Box 4, Folder 35)
    - Haskins, Caryl 1936, 1938-39, 1966, undated (Box 4, Folder 36)
    - Hassall, C. H. 1967-68 (Box 4, Folder 37)
    - Hodgkin, Dorothy Crowfoot 1938-47, 1950-53, 1969, undated (Box 4, Folder 38)
    - Howard, Evelyn 1941-43 (Box 4, Folder 39)
    - Hughes, Edward 1954, 1956, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 40)
    - Hunt, W. F. 1951, [see also Donnay correspondence] (Box 4, Folder 41)
    - I-J 1941-64 (Box 4, Folder 42)
    - Ing, H. Raymond 1936-38 (Box 4, Folder 43)
    - K 1935-70 (Box 4, Folder 44)
    - Kaempffert, Waldmar 1941, 1944, 1947 (Box 4, Folder 45)
    - Karle, Jerome and Isabella 1961-62, [see also I. Fankuchen] (Box 4, Folder 46)
    - Kenner, G. W. 1961-66 (Box 4, Folder 47)
    - L 1939-71 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Langmuir, Irving 1938-46, [see also David Harker correspondence and Misc. correspondence] (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Loeb, Arthur and Lotje 1960, 1969-70 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - M 1937-70, [see also SERIES VI. WRITINGS - Research Notes - Notes re: D'Arcy Thompson] (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Masoero, Marcella 1951, 1954-58, 1960-66 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Mauger, Tony 1962-67, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - N-P 1936-69 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Neville, Eric and Maynard, [see box 6]
    - Pacsu, Eugene 1958-65 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Patterson, A.L. 1941, 1951 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Pauling, Linus, [see Scott, William]
    - Perutz, Max 1947-1952, 1963 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Polanyi, Michael 1935, 1948 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - R 1937-67 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Reimann, Stanley 1942 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Russell, Bertrand (copies from Bertrand Russell Archives, McMaster University) 1917-1919, 1930 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - S 1934-75 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Scott, William and Linus Pauling 1956 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Marjorie Senechal 1974-75, [see also SERIES VI. WRITINGS - Research Notes - Symmetry and Twinning notes-notebook (2) and contents] (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Sobotka, Harry, [see box 6]
    - Stallybrass, C.O. 1948-1950 (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - Stoll, Arthur 1955-56, 1961 (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Swann, W.F.G. 1941-43 (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Szent-Gyorgyi, A. 1935-36 (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - T-V 1937-66, undated (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - Thompson, D'Arcy 1924, 1943, [see also SERIES VI. WRITINGS - Research Notes - Notes re: D'Arcy Thompson] (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - Vickery, Hubert Bradford 1939-70, [see also SERIES VI. WRITINGS - Research Notes - Discussion with H.B. Vickery] (Box 5, Folder 24)
    - W-Z 1934-69 (Box 5, Folder 25)
    - Williams, J.W. 1938, 1941, 1949 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Correspondence and notes with Nevilles (Eric and Maynard) and Sobotka
    - Wrinch to Eric Neville 1940-60, undated (Box 6, Folder 1-3)
    - Eric Neville to Wrinch 1940-61, undated (Box 6, Folder 4-5)
    - Notes placed with Neville lettersundated (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - With Maynard Neville regarding Eric Neville's death 1961 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Wrinch to Harry Sobotka 1937-65 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Harry Sobotka to Wrinch 1937-65 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Notes placed with Sobotka lettersundated, [see also SERIES IX. MISCELLANEOUS - Memorials: Harry Sobotka] (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Correspondence between Langmuir, Huggins, Pauling, Lamb, and Harker 1938-40 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Financial papers and purchase orders 1948-66 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Job-hunting 1940-41 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Letters of congratulations on the NSF grant 1959 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Princeton project 1946-47 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Reprint requests 1943-69 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Wedding congratulations 1941 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Unidentified (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Between Walter Dyer and Waldemar Kaempffert re: article by Otto Glaser 1941 (Box 7, Folder 9)
- SERIES IV. GRANTS 1935-66
  - National Science Foundation grants 1961-64 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Office of Naval Research: technical reports, progress reports, annual and semiannual reports, and proposals 1947-58 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Rockefeller Foundation grants correspondence 1935-40 (Box 8, Folder 3-4)
  - Applications and correspondence: Rockefeller Foundation grant and Rhodes Traveling Fellowship 1930 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous grants including abstracts 1940-66 (Box 8, Folder 6)
- SERIES V. PUBLICATIONS 1919-66, undated
  - Early math and philosophy reprints, articles, and abstracts 1919-39 (Box 9, Folder 1-2)
  - Reprints, articles, and abstracts 1940-65, undated (Box 9, Folder 3-6)
  - Newspaper articles (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Monographs
    - "Fourier Transforms and Structure Factors" and correspondence 1946, 1961-66 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - "Chemical Aspects of the Structure of Small Peptides" and correspondence and reviews 1960 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - "Chemical Aspects of the Structure of Small Peptides" and "Chemical Aspects of Polypeptide Chain Structures and the Cyclol Theory:" letters and miscellaneous material 1960-69 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - "Chemical Aspects of Polypeptide Chain Structures and the Cyclol Theory:" correspondence and reviews 1965 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - "Chemical Aspects of Polypeptide Chain Structures and the Cyclol Theory:" appendix and revisions 1965 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence and notes regarding publications of her monographs 1959-66, undated (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Monograph notes marked "monograph II"undated (Box 10, Folder 7-9)
    - Monograph notes and outlinesundated (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - Wrinch, Dorothy. "Fourier Transforms and Structure Factors." The American Society for X-ray and Electron Diffraction, February 1946. (ASXRED Monograph #2) (Reprinted by the American Crystallographic Association1966) (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - Wrinch, Dorothy. Chemical Aspects of the Structure of Small Peptides: An Introduction. Copenhagen: Munksgaard 1960. 2 copies (Box 10, Folder 12-13)
    - Wrinch, Dorothy. Chemical Aspects of Polypeptide Chain Structures and the Cyclol Theory. Copenhagen: Munksgaard 1965. 2 copies (Box 11, Folder 1-2)
  - "The Geometrical Attack on Protein Structure" (includes comments by Pauling and Niemann) 1941 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - "The Geometrical Attack on Protein Structure:" comments and notes by Wrinch and notes between Pauling and Wrinch 1938 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - "The Geometrical Attack on Protein Structure:" referee reports 1939, undated (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - "Recent Advances in Cyclol Chemistry:" illustrations and notes 1963 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Drafts of molecular diagrams for publicationsundated (Box 11, Folder 7-9)
  - Cut-outs and diagrams from various articlesundated (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Referee comments on various articles 1939-58 (Box 11, Folder 11-12)
- SERIES VI. WRITINGS 1936-70
  - Manuscripts
    - Miscellaneous technical writings 1936-65, undated (Box 12, Folder 1-3)
    - Essay "On the Structure of DNA" with notes and diagrams and correspondence from Harry Sobotka and Tony Sonneborn 1954-55 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Non-technical unpublished writings
    - "Tender Emotions," undated (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - "A Problem Play for the Adult Young," undated (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Essays concerning the directions of her work, some used for application purposes 1941-43, 1953-57, undated (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous writings and speeches 1935, 1938-41, 1951, 1954, undated (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Notecardsundated (Box 12)
  - Notebooks containing manuscripts for her book (Box 13)
  - Research notes
    - Diagrams: symmetry and twinning (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Symmetry (Box 14, Folder 2-5)
    - Twinning (Box 14, Folder 6-7)
    - Twinning: notes for companion paper with Donnay, [see also SERIES III. CORRESPONDENCE - Individuals - Jose and Gabrielle Donnay] (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - Symmetry and Twinning: "Closest Packing" (Box 14, Folder 9)
    - Symmetry and Twinning notebook contents (Box 14, Folder 10-12)
    - 6 notebooks 1930s-40s (Box 15, Folder 1-5)
    - Early peptide studies 1937-39 (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - Technical 1930s (Box 15, Folder 7)
    - Marked reprints 1930, 1933-39 (Box 15, Folder 8)
    - Cold Spring Harbor Symposia 1938 (Box 15, Folder 9)
    - Technical
      - Proteins and genetics 1940s (Box 15, Folder 10)
      - Crystallography, insulin, proteins, and cyclols 1940s (Box 15, Folder 11)
    - Non-technical 1940s (Box 15, Folder 12)
    - Marked reprints 1940s (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Non-technical 1950s (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - Technical: amino acids and crystallography 1950s (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - Marked reprints
      - With notes 1950s (Box 16, Folder 4)
      - Insulin 1950s (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - Technical
      - Bacitracin 1950s (Box 16, Folder 6)
      - Peptides, proteins, cyclols, and insulin 1960s (Box 17, Folder 1-7)
    - Notes re: D'Arcy Thompson and P.B. Medawar 1960s (Box 17, Folder 8)
    - Discussion with H.B. Vickery 1960s (Box 17, Folder 9)
    - Non-technical 1960s (Box 17, Folder 10)
    - Marked Reprints
      - Articles by Griot, Frey, Ott, and Hoffman 1963 (Box 18, Folder 1)
      - Articles by Shemyakin, Antonov, Shkrob, Sheinker, Senyavina, Shchelokov 1962-63 (Box 18, Folder 2)
      - Miscellaneous articles 1960s (Box 18, Folder 3-5)
    - Technical: Geometry in Molecular Biology, cyclohexane conformation, "whole number geometry," and miscellaneous 1970s (Box 19, Folder 1-3)
    - Non-technical (Box 19, Folder 4)
    - Miscellaneous notes: polyhedra, tobacco mosaic virus (Box 19, Folder 5-6)
    - Technicalundated (Box 19, Folder 7)
    - Non-technicalundated (Box 19, Folder 8)